All right, so today's דף *daf* is ט"ז *Tes Zayin*. We're a
little bit behind, we pick up on ט"ז עמוד ב *Tes Zayin
Amud Bais*. We are digressing a little bit because we're talking about
the Mordechai going out with לבוש מלכות *levush malchus* and we used
it as a tie-in to say that's why יוסף Yosef *Yosef* gave
five changes of garments to בנימין *Binyamin*, not because he wasn't sensitive
to the issue about jealousy and sibling rivalry, but to symbolize this.
And now we're going to sort of speak about further symbolism of
all of this,
of what was going on there or symbolizing, I don't know, anyway.
So five about eight lines from the top on ט"ז עמוד ב
*Tes Zayin Amud Bais*. ויפול על צוארי בנימין אחיו *Vayipol al tzavarei
Binyamin achiv*. So יוסף Yosef *Yosef* fell on בנימין *Binyamin*'s neck and
he cried, ובנימין בכה על צואריו *u'Binyamin bacha al tzavarav*. So כמה
צוארין הוו ליה *kama tzavarin havu leh*, what do you mean צוארי
*tzavarei* plural? How many necks did he have? Of course as Rashi
points out that's the way the Torah refers to neck, right? You
ever say pant, no it's pants, anyway, but that's a little different
because there are two pant legs, anyway. It's always in plural. But
anyway, all right, nevertheless, here's the דרשה drasha, *drasha*. אמר רבי Rebbe
אלעזר בכה על שני מקדשים שעתידין להיות בחלקו של בנימין ועתידין ליחרב
*Amar Rabbi Elazar bacha al shnei mikdashim she'atidin lihyot b'chelko shel Binyamin
v'atidin l'yecharev*. He cried for the two מקדשים *mikdashim* that would be
in בנימין *Binyamin*'s portion in the land of ישראל Yisrael? *Yisrael* and
they would be eventually destroyed. So again sort of interesting together with
the symbolism of Mordechai and the five switches of garments you have
the two מקדשים *mikdashim* and of course מגילה Megillah. *Megilla* situated between
these two מקדשים *mikdashim* according to חז"ל *Chazal*. ובנימין בכה על צואריו
*U'Binyamin bacha al tzavarav*, בנימין *Binyamin* cried on his again notice it's
צואריו *tzavarav* necks but here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is ignoring the
plural. בכה על משכן שילה שעתיד להיות בחלקו של יוסף Yosef ועתיד
ליחרב *Bacha al mishkan Shiloh she'atid lihyot b'chelko shel Yosef v'atid l'yecharev*,
also cried for the destruction of the משכן שילה *mishkan Shiloh*. So
there was a crying not just of joy but of some type
of a future destruction. והנה עיניכם רואות ועיני אחי בנימין כי פי
המדבר אליכם *V'hinei eyneichem ra'ot v'eynei achi Binyamin ki pi hamedaber aleichem*.
So אמר רבי Rebbe אלעזר אמר להם כשם שאין בלבי על בנימין
אחי שלא היה במכירתי *Amar Rabbi Elazar amar lahem k'shem she'ein b'libi
al Binyamin achi shelo haya b'mechirasi*. So right, why focusing ועיני אחי
בנימין *v'eynei achi Binyamin* separate? Again you could say that's raising some
special treatment. So no, he's making a point. The same way clearly
I have nothing against בנימין *Binyamin* because he was not in the
whole the plot to sell me, כך אין לי בלבי עליכם *kach
ein li b'libi aleichem*. I have nothing against you, I don't hold
any grudge against you. כי פי המדבר אליכם *Ki pi hamedaber aleichem*,
it is my mouth speaking to you, כפי כן לבי *k'fi ken
libi*. As I say what I say is just what's in my
heart. I am being sincere, okay. ולאביו שלח כזאת עשרה חמורים נושאים
מטוב מצרים *U'le'aviv shalach kazot asara chamorim noseim mi'tuv Mitzrayim*. So he
sent ten donkeys carrying all of the good of Egypt. מאי מטוב
מצרים *Mai mi'tuv Mitzrayim*, what's the good of Egypt? אמר רבי rebbe
בנימין בר יפת אמר רבי Rebbi? אלעזר שלח לו יין ישן שדעת
זקנים נוחה הימנו *Amar Rabbi Binyamin bar Yefet amar Rabbi Elazar shalach
lo yayin yashan she'da'at zekenim nocha heymenu*. He sent good old wine
which is elderly people really can appreciate or makes them puts them
in a good state of mind, okay. וילכו גם אחיו ויפלו לפניו
*Vayelchu gam achiv vayiplu lefanav*. This is at the end now right
after after יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* dies they prostrate themselves and they say
you know they don't know exactly now maybe יוסף Yosef *Yosef* will
take it out on them and so they prostrate themselves before him.
אמר רבי Rebbi בנימין בר יפת אמר רבי Rebbi אלעזר *Amar Rabbi
Binyamin bar Yefet amar Rabbi Elazar*. Notice by the way a lot
of these are רבי Rebbi בנימין בר יפת *Rabbi Binyamin bar Yefet*
or רבי Rebbi אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*, רבי בנימין בר יפת *Rabbi Binyamin
bar Yefet* in the name of רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. Anyway, היינו
דאמרי אינשי *hainu d'amri inshi*, this is what people say תעלא בעידניה
סגיד ליה *ta'ala b'idneih sagid leh*. A fox when he has his
time you know when he's when he has things going his way
you have to lower yourself you have to prostrate yourself to him.
So they were willing to prostrate themselves to יוסף Yosef *Yosef* because
יוסף Yosef *Yosef* had the power. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says
תעלא *ta'ala*, a fox? מאי בצירותיה מאחוה *Mai betzirosieh me'achvoh*, how was
he worse than his brothers? Meaning he was equal like you could
say he should have been their equal but now he had power
so he was you know somebody they had to show honor to
or subjugate themselves to but he wasn't a fox, a fox suggests
somebody who's at a lower level. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר *Ela
ei ismar hachi ismar*, if it was said here's the better context
in which it was said, וישתחו ישראל על ראש המטה *vayishtachu Yisrael
al rosh hamitah*. ישראל *Yisrael* bowed down on the bed this is
when he calls יוסף *Yosef* to him and he's going to bring
you know אפרים *Ephraim* and מנשה *Menashe* give them the blessing. So
אמר רבי בנימין בר יפת אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Binyamin bar
Yefet amar Rabbi Elazar*, here's where you should make the statement, תעלא
בעידניה סגיד ליה *ta'ala b'idneih sagid leh*. So יוסף *Yosef* who clearly
was יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*'s son what's יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* doing bowing down
to? Because even a fox has his day and it was יוסף
*Yosef* was in power so you have to recognize that. וינחם אותם
וידבר vayidaber, על לבם *Vaynachim otam vayidaber al libam*, back to the
brothers who now are prostrating themselves before יוסף *Yosef* and saying you
know
we're slaves to you don't do anything to us so he consoled
them. אמר רבי בנימין בר יפת אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Binyamin
bar Yefet amar Rabbi Elazar* again, a lot of רבי בנימין בר
יפת אמר רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Binyamin bar Yefet amar Rabbi Elazar*, presumably
he gave a דרשה drasha *drasha* explaining the whole you know the
whole יוסף *Yosef* story. He was an early תנא *Tanna* man, okay.
מלמד *Melamed*, he said to them דברים שמתקבלים על הלב *devarim she'miskablim
al halev*. So וידבר על לבם means that sometimes it's not enough
just to make, say, say something, you have to do it in
a way that people can hear and that they'll, that'll make an
emotional impact. And here's what he said: ומה עשרה נרות לא יכלו
לכבות נר אחד, u-mah asarah nerot lo yakhlu lekhabot ner echad, ten
candles could not extinguish one candle. You all together could not extinguish
me. נר אחד היאך יכול לכבות עשרה נרות, ner echad heikh yakhol
lekhabot asarah nerot, how could one candle extinguish ten? Of course he
has a lot of political power that they didn't have. Okay, but
the point was that by framing it as נרות, nerot, he's framing
it in terms of, like, you know, the soul and on a
spiritual level. And therefore, it's all about the spiritual plane and clearly
therefore I cannot, I will not, you know, I don't even have
the power. Not only will I not use it, I wouldn't even
be able to even if I were to try to use it.
Okay, so that's ending that digression. Back to the מגילה. Megilla, ליהודים
היתה אורה ושמחה וששון ויקר. layehudim hayetah orah vesimkhah vesason vikar.
It was a nice time with the נר ner and with the
wine and with whatever. Okay, ליהודים היתה אורה ושמחה וששון ויקר. layehudim
hayetah orah vesimkhah vesason vikar.
To the Jews there was light and joy and rejoicing and honor.
So אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehudah, אורה זו תורה, orah zo
Torah, light means תורה. Torah. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, כי
נר מצוה
ותורה אור. ki ner mitzvah ve-Torah or. So there's the נר ner
again. A מצוה mitzvah is a candle and תורה Torah is light.
שמחה זה יום טוב, simkhah zeh Yom Tov, שמחה simkhah is a
יום טוב. Yom Tov. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, ושמחת בחגך.
vesamakhta be-khagekha. ששון זו מילה, sason zo milah,
rejoicing is מילה. milah. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, שש אנכי
על אמרתך כמוצא שלל רב, sas anokhi al imratekha kemotze shalul rav,
which we say at a ברית מילה. bris milah. And רש"י Rashi
points out that when God commands the ברית מילה bris milah to
אברהם, Avraham, it doesn't say וידבר, it says ויאמר, vayomer, ויאמר, vayomer,
ויאמר. vayomer. So that's אמרתך. imratekha. ויקר אלו תפילין, vikar elu tefillin,
glory is תפילין. tefillin. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, וראו כל
עמי הארץ כי שם ה' נקרא עליך ויראו ממך. verau kol amei
ha-aretz ki shem Hashem nikra alekha ve-yar'u mimmeka. They'll see it and
they'll be afraid of you. So that's the idea of like glory
in something that like has, you know, an impact on anyone who
looks at it. Now, what does all this have to do with
anything? So what does it mean, so that they had a rejoicing
and a party and they put on תפילין tefillin and learned תורה?
Torah? So רש"י Rashi says, you know, that reads this as the
גמרא Gemara, is indicating that המן Haman not only made a decree
to wipe out the Jews, but that he also, like as we
know in the time of, in the time of what do you
call it, of the חנוכה Chanukah story and other times, he made
a decree also to prohibit religious activities. So for example, רש"י Rashi
says, two lines down in the נר ner lines on the right-hand
side, אורה זו תורה שגזר עליהם המן שלא יעסקו בתורה. orah zo
Torah shegazar aleihem Haman shelo yaasku ba-Torah. Okay, by יום טוב Yom
Tov he says קימו עליהם ימים טובים, kimu aleihem yamim tovim, which
might just mean again the יום טוב. Yom Tov. Of course, by
יום טוב Yom Tov you could tie it into the fact that
they initially wanted פורים Purim to be a יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Okay, but then if you look at the next רש"י, Rashi, זו
מילה ועל כל אלו גזר. zo milah ve'al kol elu gazar. So
here the גמרא, Gemara you know, is sort of conflating to some
degree the theme of חנוכה Chanukah and the theme of פורים. Purim.
I don't seem to see there is another explanation for this. So
that's okay. ותניא, vetanya, we learned in a ברייתא, beraita, I'm sorry,
yes, I'm sorry. Okay, ואת פרשנדתא, ve'et Parshandasa, continuing now back in
the גמרא, Gemara. ואת פרשנדתא, ve'et Parshandasa, so עשרת בני המן. aseret
benei Haman. So אמר רב אדא דמן יפו, amar Rav Adda demin
Yafo, עשרת בני המן ועשרת, aseret benei Haman ve-aseret, when you say
the ten names of the sons of המן Haman and then you
say the word עשרת, aseret, צריך למימרינהו בנשימה אחת. tzarikh lemimreinhu beneshimah
akhat. You have to say them all in one breath. מאי טעמא,
mai taama, what's the reason? כולהו בהדי הדדי נפקא נשמתייהו kulu behadi
hadadi nafka nishmatayhu because their breath, their soul, all departed in one
instant. They were all hanged at the same time, and to symbolize
this, you have to hold your, you know, say it all in
one breath. Presumably, that somehow shows some miracle or somehow some divine,
you know, role within what happened. I don't know. So somehow there's
some significance in the fact that they all died at the same
time. And 70 children? Exactly. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, צריך
לומר בנשימה אחת, tzarikh lomar beneshimah akhat, תוספות Tosafot says נראה דהיינו
לכתחילה אבל בדיעבד יצא. nireh de-hainu le-khatchilah aval be-diavad yatza. So okay,
I heard, I know somebody once has a position that, I don't
know what people, you know, the fact that we all sort of,
the בעל קורא ba'al korei stops and then everybody says it is
presumably based on, I don't know, maybe the other reasons given, presumably
his breath? No, maybe, but presumably it's based on the idea that
although you're יוצא קריאת מגילה yotze krias Megillah by somebody else reading
because of the principle of שומע כעונה, shomea k'oneh, listening is like
you said it, but having somebody hold their breath is not like
you held your breath. So therefore you have to say it yourself
all in one breath. What I do is I just hold my
breath as the חזן chazzan is saying עשרת בני המן. aseret benei
Haman.
Anyway, so that's where you get that from. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rabi Yochanan, ו של ויזתא, vav shel Vaizasa, right, ו של
ויזתא, vav shel Vaizasa, צריך לממתחה בזקיפא כמורדיא דלברות. tzarikh lemimtechah bezikifa
kemordya dilvros.
You have to stretch it out like long, the ו vav of
ויזתא, Vaizasa, like the, like the pole used, like a river pole
used in this river called לברות. Livros. Stretching the vav?
Or you mean
the כתיבה?
kesivah? I think לממתחה, lemimtechah, yeah, it seems to be the כתיבה,
kesivah, might be because it's a visual thing. מאי טעמא, mai taama,
כולהו בחד זקיפא אזדקיפו. kulu bechad zikifa izdakaifu.
They were all hanged on the same pole. So therefore you have
to sort of symbolize the gallows, which is interesting. Interesting that you're
making a change
in the actual way something is written because of this type of
idea of let's have it symbolize. Doesn't sound like there was a
מסורה Masora to write it big, it sounds like it starts with
he wants this symbolism and therefore you have to write it this
way, which is very bizarre because normally the tradition of how the
letters are written or whatever, you know, exists independently of various interpretive
traditions. I should also say a mention about the fact that we
do them all, you know, let's do one more thing about that.
Then the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא
Amar Rabbi Chanina Bar Pappa said רבי חנינא בר פפא Rabbi Chanina
Bar Pappa דרש ההוא איש כפר תמרא Darash Hahu Ish Kfar Timra
of the village of Timra, כל השירות כולן נכתבות אריח על גבי
לבינה, Kol Hashirot Kulan Nichtavot Ariach Al Gabei Levina,
all of the other poems or songs in the תנ"ך Tanach are
written like the a half brick on top of a full brick,
ולבינה על גבי אריח, Ulevina Al Gabei Ariach, and a full brick
on top of a half brick. Meaning, you know, if you see
the way that normally, right, brick is laid, right, how is brick
laid? Right, brick is normally laid like this, right? Yes. Right? So
like alternates, right? So if you look at a normal שירה, Shira,
right, if you look at for example
האזינו, Ha'azinu, the way it's written in the תורה, Torah, not האזינו;
Ha'azinu; האזינו Ha'azinu is the exception, excuse me, אז ישיר, Az Yashir,
right,
so that's the way it looks, right? Yeah. Okay, so that's why
it's sort of, it's not exactly half brick on a full brick,
but it means staggered, okay? So all of the poems and songs
in the תנ"ך Tanach are staggered חוץ Chutz with the exception משירה
זו Mishira Zo and I know it's called שירה Shira again, שירה
Shira sort of means anything written in a, you know, in a
this, anything other than a straight prose form of being written, but
the listing of the עשרת בני המן, Aseret Bnei Haman, funny to
call it a שירה. Shira.
But anyway ומלכי כנען Umalchei Kna'an and when it lists the kings
of כנען, Kna'an, שאריח על גבי אריח ולבינה על גבי לבינה She'ariach
Al Gabei Ariach Ulevina Al Gabei Levina that there it appears, and
it's funny he says only this because this is also the way
it appears by האזינו, Ha'azinu, right? It's like this, right, with a
big white space in the middle, which by the way, it always
seemed to me that if there was anything that was going to
be written like this, it should have been שירת הים Shirat Hayam
because, yeah right, it comes from the sea. Anyway, okay.
And the column in האזינו Ha'azinu is also wider.
Right, well that's because each stanza is very short, so I mean
each half פסוק Pasuk is so short.
Anyway, so he says, why does he say האזינו? Ha'azinu?
I don't know, because it doesn't fit with the point he's about
to make. So everything except for another exception, okay? So מאי טעמא
Mai Ta'ama why? שלא תהא תקומה למפלתן Shelo Tehe Tkuma Lemapaltan that
there should not be any rising up to their falling, so it's
very unsteady, of course, that's why they lay bricks in not like
this, because that's highly unsteady, so it means it should be a
complete falling. So one more thing though about the עשרת בני המן,
Aseret Bnei Haman, which is, is that there's, you know, the other
sort of tradition of עשרת בני המן Aseret Bnei Haman not mentioned
here is that it all has to
fill up a column, right? Because otherwise it would look, I mean,
I don't know, would it look so funny? We have like the
end of, you know, other שירות Shirot that begin like this and
then the text continues below. Even in שירת הים. Shirat Hayam. Yeah,
שירת הים Shirat Hayam or whatever. Anyway, but the tradition is it
all has to fill up a column. So for most people what
they wind up doing, right, is they wind up writing very large
letters for the עשרת בני המן Aseret Bnei Haman to fill up
a column, which הגר"א HaGra is very opposed to because he says
we have certain traditions about how the letters are written like a
big ו Vav for ויזתא Vaizata but we don't have any מסורה
Masora that you write עשרת בני המן Aseret Bnei Haman in a
larger font than the rest of the script, and normally you need
a מסורה Masora of writing to say that you write certain letters
larger. So what I have when I bought a מגילה, Megilla I
bought my wife's תור Tor מגילה Megilla
many years ago, so I had to decide like which of the
various הידורים, Hidurim, you know, to look for. So the one that
most people go for is the המלך מגילה Hamelech Megilla because some
brilliant person figured out that after the first פסוק Pasuk there the
word המלך Hamelech appears so many times in the מגילה Megilla that
you could actually break it up, you know, so that המלך Hamelech
appears at the beginning of every single column. And you know, and
the same size columns. So that's like a classic thing people do,
but there's no like הלכתי Halachic basis for that, as a הידור,
Hidur, but it's nice. Anyway, so what I said, but I went
with a more הלכתי Halachic הידור Hidur and the more הלכתי Halachic
הידור Hidur is the a מגילה Megilla that only has 11
rows of text per column. Why is that a הידור? Hidur? Because
then when you get to the עשרת בני המן Aseret Bnei Haman
you can write all the עשרת בני המן Aseret Bnei Haman and
then the word ועשרת, Ve'aseret, right, you can write them all in
a filling up a column without having to make them bigger. So
now every time it comes time to do the מגילה Megilla. it's
like so much scrolling. It's a
really long מגילה. Megilla. Really long. Anyway, okay. So that's about the
עשרת בני המן. Aseret Bnei Haman. All right, so back to the
גמרא. Gemara What?
Did he actually say you're not allowed to write it out larger?
It isn't that it's פסול, Pasul, but he says it's
I'm not sure what he does the consequences, but yes, he says
that that's not the writing of a מגילה. Megilla That's not the
way a מגילה Megilla, should be written. Okay. So back to the
back to דרשנינג Darshening the פסוקים. Psukim. Okay. ויאמר המלך לאסתר המלכה
בשושן הבירה הרגו יהודים ואבד חמש מאות איש Vayomer Hamelech Le'ester Hamalka
Beshushan Habira Hargu Yehudim Ve'abed Chamesh Meot Ish and you know, and
you know, so oh my god, look what they've done, they've killed
people. בשאר מדינות המלך מה עשו Bish'ar Medinot Hamelech Ma Asu and
you, ואת מה שאלתך ותינתן לך Ve'et Ma She'elatach Vetinatein Lach what
do you want? Obviously there's a major... shift in tone from the
beginning of the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* to the end of the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*. So אמר רבי אבהו *Amar Rabbi Abbahu* מלמד שבא מלאך
וסטרו על פיו *melamed sheba malach v'stah'o al piv* the angel came
the same way the angel moved Esther's hand at the critical moment,
the angel came and slapped אחשורוש *Achashverosh* in his mouth and therefore
he switched his tone in the middle of his sentence because it
is a very strange פסוק *pasuk*, right, that he shifts. So he's
incensed and then he says but you anything you want, Esther. Okay.
ובבואה לפני המלך *Uvevo'ah lifnei hamelech*, when she came before the king,
אמר עם הספר *amar im hasefer*, he said with the with the,
you know, with the book, ישוב מחשבתו הרעה *yashuv machshavto hara'ah* you
know, אשר חשב *Asher Chashav*. So who's the who is saying this?
So it sounds like it's the king saying it, like she came
before the king, the king retracted. Well, it wasn't exactly the king
who retracted, it was Mordechai who retracted. So אמר עם הספר *Amar
Im Hasefer*, he said it should be. So אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar
Rabbi Yochanan*, אמרה לו *amra lo*, יאמר בפה מה שכתוב בספר *yomar
bepeh mah shekatuv basefer*. So she said to him, Rashi takes out
the words אמרה לו *amra lo* because who's she saying to, saying
to Mordechai, saying to the king. He takes out those words. He
just has it says יאמר בפה מה שכתוב בספר *yomar bepeh mah
shekatuv basefer* that you you should say over verbally what is written
in the book, which means what? So if you take a look
at Rashi, Rashi says the following. He says הכי גרסינן *haichi garsinan*
at the end of the right-hand column, אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav
Nachman*, יאמר בפה מה שכתוב בספרים *yomar bepeh mah shekatuv basefarim* ולא
גרסינן אמרה לו *v'lo garsinan amra lo*. והכי פירוש סדר מקראות *Ve'hachi
perush seder mikra'ot*, כך הוא *kach hu*. וקבל היהודים את אשר החלו
לעשות *V'kibel hayehudim et asher hechilu la'asot*, they accepted the practice of
doing Purim. כי המן בן המדתא האגגי *Ki Haman ben Hamedata ha'Agagi*,
top of the left-hand column, you know, wanted to do all of
these things ובבואה לפני המלך *uvevo'ah lifnei hamelech*, when Esther came before
the king, אמר עם הספר *amar im hasefer*. Mordechai, ומרדכי כתב עליהם
*u'Mordechai katav aleihem*, so now the subject, it switches is you know,
שיעשו פורים Purim, כי המן ביקש לאבדם *sheya'asu Purim ki Haman bikesh
le'abdam* ומה שביקשה אסתר Esther לפני המלך להתחנן לו *u'mah shebikesha Esther
lifnei hamelech lehitchanen lo*, כל זה יאמר שנה בשנה *kol zeh yomar
shanah beshanah*. So the way he's reading it is אמר *amar*, it
switches it to אמר *amar*, right, I'm sorry, let me just see,
yeah, יאמר בפה *yomar bepeh*, so it's אמר *amar* Mordechai said, you
know, or or it was that you should say, you know, אמר
*amar*, I'm sorry, I lost the place. יאמר בפה מה שכתוב בספר
*yomar bepeh mah shekatuv basefer*, you should say out loud what is
written, meaning sort of reading it in terms of, let me see,
עם הספר *im hasefer*. No, nobody said it to anybody, it's sort
of talking about the practice of Purim. Hold on, let me let
me get this again. Where is it? כי המן בן המדתא האגגי
צורר כל היהודים חשב על היהודים לאבדם *Ki Haman ben Hamedata ha'Agagi
tzorrer kol hayehudim chashav al hayehudim le'abdam* והפיל פור הוא הגורל להמם
ולאבדם *v'hippil pur hu hagoral lehumam u'le'abdam*. ובבואה לפני המלך *Uvevo'ah lifnei
hamelech*, אמר עם הספר *amar im hasefer* ישוב מחשבתו הרעה אשר חשב
על היהודים על ראשו ותלו אותו ואת בניו על העץ *yashuv machshavto
hara'ah asher chashav al hayehudim al rosho vetalu oto ve'et banav al
ha'etz*. I don't know, I'm not sure how he's reading it. One
minute. I thought
I thought I made sense when I prepared this גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*.
One minute.
Anyway, somehow it's אמר עם הספר *amar im hasefer*, we should say
this and we should recite this from the from the מגילה Megilla
*Megillah*. I think it's, how do they translate it? What do they
do with that in the Artscroll? Do you see how they translate
that?
אמרה לו לאחשורוש *Amra lo l'Achashverosh*, יאמר בפה גם בפקודה שבעל פה
מה שכתוב בספר *yomar bepeh gam bipkudah shebe'al peh mah shekatuv basefer*.
Oh, so it's just that she said to אחשורוש *Achashverosh* that he
should orally proclaim the same thing that was being written that was
sent out in the letters? That's how she reads
it?
And from memory you should read it.
Yeah, so what you're saying is I think closer to אמרה לו
*amra lo* גירסא *girsa*. So what he's saying is what Rashi is
getting at that it's just some way of referring to the reading
of the מגילה Megilla. *Megillah*, that you should say מה עם הספר
*mah im hasefer*, you should say
in here the מגילה Megilla *Megillah* out of the you know, read
it out of the מגילה Megilla *Megillah*. Okay, let's continue. Okay, so
דברי שלום ואמת *divrei shalom ve'emet*, אמר רבי תנחום ואמרי לה אמר
רבי אסי *Amar Rabbi Tanchum ve'amri lah Amar Rabbi Assi*, מלמד שצריכה
שרטוט כאמיתה של תורה Torah *melamed shetzricha sirtut ka'amittah shel Torah*. So
the מזוזה *mezuzah* needs to have lines in it like you know
you make these lines like indented lines not not with ink, but
like with an indentation the same way you do by the truth
of the Torah. So now what's the truth of the Torah? So
Rashi says אמיתה של תורה Torah, *amittah shel Torah*, Rashi says means
a ספר sefer תורה Torah? *Sefer Torah*. Tosafot disagrees with this, he
actually says that technically a ספר sefer, תורה Torah *Sefer Torah* does
not need שרטוט *sirtut* and that this actually is talking about a
מזוזה *mezuzah*. But either way, again this gets back to a theme
we began earlier about sort of Esther as you know, the ספרי
קודש *Sifrei Kodesh* and here being compared to אמיתה של תורה Torah
*amittah shel Torah*. And a point we're going to get to soon
hopefully is also like remind you the question about what language the
מגילה Megilla *Megillah* is written in. That while the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
in theory or the משנה *Mishnah* in theory recognize that the ספרים
*Sefarim* could be written in a wide range of languages, you know,
the תפילין *Tefillin* and you know could not and the מזוזה *mezuzah*
could not and the other thing that could not was the מגילה
*Megillah*. So again, like giving it like sort of much more even
heavier weight than other parts of the Torah, Tosafot sees the same
truth here about the issue of the שרטוט *sirtut*. Okay. Okay, so
now it says, where were we? ומאמר אסתר קיים, Um'amar Esther kiyam.
מאמר, Ma'amar, דברי הפורים האלה. Divrei ha-Purim ha-eleh. So the גמרא Gemara
says ומאמר אסתר Um'amar Esther קיים.
ומאמר אסתר אין דברי הצומות לא? Um'amar Esther in divrei ha-tzomot lo?
How about the fact, you know, דברי הצומות וזעקתם, divrei ha-tzomot ve-za'akatam,
right? What's the פסוק? The פסוק is
לקיים את דברי הפורים האלה בזמניהם כאשר קיים עליהם מרדכי היהודי ואסתר
המלכה וכאשר קימו על נפשם ועל זרעם דברי הצומות וזעקתם. Lekayem et
divrei ha-purim ha-eleh bizmaneihem ka'asher kiyam aleihem Mordechai ha-Yehudi ve-Esther ha-Malka ve-ka'asher
kiyemu al nafsham ve-al zar'am divrei ha-tzomot u-za'akatam. So they accepted, you
know, upon themselves just the way they, you know, the Jews at
that time accepted the fasts and their crying out. ומאמר אסתר קיים
דברי הפורים האלה. Um'amar Esther kiyam divrei ha-Purim ha-eleh. And they accepted
מאמר אסתר, Ma'amar Esther, well what about the צומות? tzomot?
So the גמרא Gemara
says, so let's take a look. So אמר רבי יוחנן דברי הצומות
ומאמר אסתר קיים, Amar Rabbi Yochanan divrei ha-tzomot u-ma'amar Esther kiyam, ימי,
yemei, so meaning you don't put the period at דברי הצומות וזעקתם.
ומאמר אסתר divrei ha-tzomot ve-za'akatam u-ma'amar Esther, is a continuation of what
appeared beforehand. So דברי הצומות וזעקתם ומאמר אסתר קיים דברי הפורים האלה.
Divrei ha-tzomot ve-za'akatam u-ma'amar Esther kiyam divrei ha-Purim ha-eleh. Now the question
is it sounds like it means that the Jews accepted to do
a fast day, even though the whole idea of תענית אסתר Taanit
Esther is post-גמרא. Gemara So if you take a look, רש"י Rashi
does not read it as accepting the practice of a fast. If
you take a look, רש"י Rashi says,
no, רש"י Rashi doesn't say it here. Okay, but anyway, but someone
says that the point here meaning that it is through the fasting
and through the words of אסתר Esther, that קיים דברי הפורים האלה,
kiyam divrei ha-Purim ha-eleh, through that led to the fulfillment of these
words of פורים, Purim, the story of the פורים, Purim. right? So
I mean, the way the English translates it is, and Esther's ordinance
validating these observances of Purim were recorded in a scroll. But it
seems the way the גמרא's Gemara reading it is that they were
מקיים mekayem on themselves the same way כאשר קיים עליהם מרדכי היהודי
ואסתר המלכה וכאשר קימו על נפשם, ka'asher kiyam aleihem Mordechai ha-Yehudi ve-Esther
ha-Malka ve-ka'asher kiyemu al nafsham, the same way it was originally observed,
דברי הצומות וזעקתם divrei ha-tzomot ve-za'akatam. ומאמר אסתר, the crying out and
the edicts of אסתר, קיים דברי הפורים האלה kiyam divrei ha-Purim ha-eleh
were like, you know, ultimately validated or brought about these days of
פורים. Purim. So it's reading it as a, as a sort of
historical, you know, reference to what led to the, to the actual
miracle of פורים. Purim Okay, moving
up. כי מרדכי היהודי משנה למלך אחשורוש, Ki Mordechai ha-Yehudi mishneh la-melech
Achashverosh, וגדול ליהודים ורצוי לרוב אחיו. ve-gadol la-Yehudim ve-ratzui le-rov echav. לרוב
אחיו ולא לכל אחיו, Le-rov echav ve-lo le-chol echav, only most and
that famous מדרש, Midrash, not all, מלמד שפירשו ממנו מקצת סנהדרין. melamed
she-pirshu mimenu miktzat Sanhedrin. Some of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin didn't want anything
to do with him anymore because he had left the בית מדרש.
beit midrash. אמר רב יוסף גדול תלמוד תורה יותר מהצלת נפשות. Amar
Rav Yosef gadol talmud Torah yoter me-hatzalat nefashot. תורה Torah is greater
than saving souls. דמעיקרא חשיב ליה למרדכי בתר ארבעה. De-me'ikara chashev leh
le-Mordechai batar arba'ah. Originally in עזרא Ezra when it lists מרדכי, Mordechai,
it lists him after four great people. ולבסוף בתר חמישה, U-levasof batar
chamishah, and later after the פורים Purim story, he comes only after
five. He went down in his
status. מעיקרא כתיב אשר באו עם זרובבל ישוע נחמיה שריה רעליה מרדכי
בלשן. Me'ikara ktiv asher ba'u im Zerubavel Yeshua Nechemiah Serayah Re'elayah Mordechai
Bilshan. So he's after four, he's number five. ולבסוף כתיב U-levasof ktiv
and then later in פסוקים psukim which simply happen after the פורים
story it
says, הבאים עם זרובבל ישוע נחמיה עזריה רעמיה
נחמני מרדכי בלשן. ha-ba'im im Zerubavel Yeshua Nechemiah Azaryah Ra'amyah Nachamani Mordechai
Bilshan. So he's number six on the list, not number five. So
I should say, well we'll read a little bit more, so I
should say about this is quite interesting because you remember the גמרא
Gemara started with the idea that you're מבטלין תלמוד תורה מפני מקרא
מגילה, mevatlin talmud Torah mipnei mikra megillah, right? And actually you gave
the מקרא מגילה mikra megillah more importance than the מצוה mitzvah of
תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah. Here it's sort of doing the reverse. It's
not only are the people sort of, it's one thing about the
common perception, ah, you're no longer a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
you went to go into a job in politics. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara, doesn't just leave it as the people's perception, it also
says actually in fact he went down a level because now he's
not just involved in תורה, Torah he's got himself involved in other
things. So I do find it as a, you know, interesting contrast
to the way it opened, you know, and it's also a bizarre
statement. I mean, does גמרא Gemara's mean to take it literally, יותר
מהצלת נפשות? yoter me-hatzalat nefashot? So you have the opportunity to save
a life, you should say no, I have to sit and learn
תורה? Torah. Clearly that's not the הלכה. halacha. So you know, these
statements I think are more meant rhetorically than הלכתית, halachically, but it's
about this sort of like ongoing tension about keeping the idea of
תורה Torah? as the primacy of תורה Torah and at the same
time recognizing, you know, that sometimes other things, you know, do take
precedence.
Charlie? Just to say the leader of the ש"ס Shas party just
this week said that we should bolster the ישיבות yeshivot because the
תורה Torah study will protect Israel.
There you go.
And it continues with the David Letterman top ten numbers, you know,
because you know we have the beautiful women of the world and
then the top ten important.
All right, so it's a listing of who's most important, correct. The
top five, the top six. Okay, so now we end this פרק
perek with this discussion about how important תלמוד תורה talmud Torah is.
And let's take a look. אמר רבא ואיתימא רב שמואל בר מרתא
גדול תלמוד תורה יותר מבנין בית המקדש. Amar Rava ve-itayma Rav Shmuel
bar Marta gadol talmud Torah yoter mi-binyan Beit ha-Mikdash. Greater is תלמוד
תורה, talmud Torah, greater than the building of the בית המקדש. Beit
ha-Mikdash. שכל זמן שברוך בן נריה קיים לא הניחו. She-kol zman she-Baruch
ben Neriah kayam lo hinicho. עזרא ועלה. Ezra ve'ala. Why is it
that ברוך בן נריה, Baruch ben Neriya, right, I'm sorry, why is
it that, excuse me, עזרא Ezra
only came to during the, you know, when, you know, to rebuild
the second בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and the returning, you know, only
after the prophecy had started for many, many years? What was he
doing staying in בבל? Bavel? You know, he only came in the
second wave, he wasn't in the first wave. And the answer is,
is because his רבי was still alive in בבל Bavel and he
had to still be in ישיבה. Yeshiva. It wasn't yet time for
him to come, which works for עזרא Ezra who's like עזרא הסופר,
Ezra Hasofer, so he had to finish. But he was the sort
of representing תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and the whole, like I said,
the proto-rabbinic. But the גמרא's Gemara dealing with a problem of עזרא
Ezra such a leader, why did he only come in the second
wave? And the answer is, cause he was busy, he didn't want
to leave בבל Bavel where he was learning תורה Torah until his
רבי had died. אמר רבא אמר רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא,
Amar Rava amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta, and by the
way, that's touching on the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash theme also that
we dealt with earlier, right? So and the whole centrality of the
מקדש. Mikdash. So all of these themes that we have been raising
as very centrally significant, right, מקרא מגילה, Mikra Megillah, בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, and you know, here, and by the way, the הלכה halakhah
is also guess what else you're מבטל, mivatel, you know, in order
to do בנין בית המקדש? binyan Beit Hamikdash? תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah.
Okay, so you're מבטל mivatel תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah for מקרא מגילה,
Mikra Megillah, you're מבטל mivatel תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah for בנין בית
המקדש, binyan Beit Hamikdash, and nevertheless, the end סוגיא sugya and these
are the themes that have been the central aspects of the פרק
perek until now, מקרא מגילה, Mikra Megillah, בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and
so on, and here we're being told that תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
is more important than all of them. So you know, I don't
think that there's necessarily a resolution to it. It sort of reminds
me of like certain sections in ברכות Brachot where there's a big
emphasis on the importance of תפילה tfila and then somewhat at the
end, you know, it sort of gets to the importance of תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, that there's this sort of ongoing dialectic and you
know, and the Rabbis cannot have us, you know, ever having sort
of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah clearly on lower in the hierarchy. So
it's not like it's, you know, it's not like it's black and
white. We had the other voices earlier, but we have to maintain
that tension. And again, it's quite interesting that these two things, the
actual הלכה halakhah is you are מבטל mivatel תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
in order to do this.
Is this recorded anywhere in the responsa in contemporary times?
Yeah,
I mean it sort of goes back to Charlie's point.
You know, I don't know, I'd have to find out. The funny
thing, it is aggadic, like I said, it's not halakhic, the הלכה
halakhah is actually different, but the whole point of אגדתא aggadeta is
to change, to shape attitudes, you know, and then how does that
lead to interpretation of other areas of הלכה? halakhah? So again, I
think that that, you know, is important. It gets to another theme
as well which is also, you know, many contemporary sort of scholars
have pointed out the use of אגדתא aggadeta as a counter-voice to
certain הלכות. halakhot. That sometimes the גמרא Gemara very specifically juxtaposes an
אגדתא aggadeta with a הלכה halakhah to sort of speak about how,
you know, there's other sort of themes that are not being addressed
and that actually, you know, it's not as black and white as
just הלכה. halakhah. There are intentions. What? רב אשי? Rav Ashi? Well,
yeah, okay, that would be a good example. Right, you're supposed to
get as drunk עד דלא ידע, ad d'lo yada, and then you
have the story of right, of רבה Rava שחט shachting רבי זירא.
Rabbi Zeira. So which is it, right? So that exactly to maintain
that type of tension and it seems something similar's going on here.
אמר רבא בר בר רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא, Amar Rava
bar bar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta, גדול תלמוד תורה יותר
מכיבוד אב ואם. gadol Talmud Torah yoter mi-kibbud av va-em. תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah is greater than כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av va-em, שכל
אותן שנים
שהיה יעקב אבינו בבית עבר לא נענש. she-kol otan shanim she-haya Yaakov
Avinu b'veit Ever lo ne'enash. As long as יעקב Yaakov was learning
in the ישיבה Yeshiva of עבר, Ever, but you didn't know יעקב
Yaakov was learning in the ישיבה Yeshiva of עבר? Ever? You did
if you do רש"י Rashi on תורה. Torah Anyway, he was not
punished. דאמר מר, De'amar mar, yeah, okay, well, okay, that's true, fine,
דאמר מר. de'amar mar. But it means he was justified not being
with his father and he didn't get punished, so at least if
it justifies it, presumably that means that it's more important, but you're
right, maybe it's equally important. למה נמנו שנותיו של ישמעאל? Lama nimnu
shnotav shel Yishmael? Why were the years of ישמעאל Yishmael mentioned in
the תורה? Torah. Who cares how long ישמעאל Yishmael lived? כדי לייחס
בין שנותיו של יעקב, Kidei l'yacheis bein shnotav shel Yaakov, so we
can figure out יעקב's Yaakov sort of age. דכתיב ואלה שני חיי
ישמעאל מאת שנה ושלושים שנה ושבע שנים. Dichviv eleh shenei chayei Yishmael
me'at shana u-shloshim shana v'sheva shanim. So ישמעאל Yishmael was 137 when
he died.
כמה קשיש ישמעאל
מיצחק?
Kama kashish Yishmael
mi-Yitzchak? Now, how much older was ישמעאל Yishmael than יצחק? Yitzchak? ארבע
עשרה שנים, Arba-esrei shanim, 14 years. דכתיב ואברהם בן שמונים שנה ושש
שנים בלדת הגר את ישמעאל לאברהם. Dichviv v'Avraham ben shemonim shana v'shesh
shanim b'ledet Hagar et Yishmael l'Avraham. He was 86 when ישמעאל Yishmael
was born. דכתיב ואברהם בן מאת שנה בהיולד לו את יצחק בנו,
Dichviv v'Avraham ben me'at shana b'hivaled lo et Yitzchak b'no, and
he was 100 when יצחק Yitzchak was born, so יצחק Yitzchak was
so ישמעאל Yishmael was 14 years older than יצחק. Yitzchak. דכתיב ויצחק
בן ששים שנה בלדת אותם. Dichviv Yitzchak ben shishim shana b'ledet otam.
יצחק Yitzchak was 60 when יעקב Yaakov and עשו Esav were born.
Now, בר כמה הוה ישמעאל כדיתילד יעקב? Bar kama hava Yishmael kide'ityalid
Yaakov? So how old was ישמעאל, Yishmael, יצחק Yitzchak was 60, how
old was ישמעאל Yishmael when יעקב Yaakov was born? בר שבעין וארבע,
Bar shiv'in v'arba, 74, he was 14 years older. Okay, all of
this is פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. Now, כמה פיישן משני?
Kama payshan mi-shnei? ששים ושלש. Shishim v'shalosh. How much longer did ישמעאל
Yishmael have to live? 63
years.
So basically יצחק Yitzchak was sixty when יעקב Yaakov was born,
okay, when יעקב Yaakov was born, and ישמעאל Yishmael is
seventy-four, that's fourteen years old, right, which we know straight from the
פסוקים. psukim. So now from the time יעקב Yaakov was
born, zero, יצחק Yitzchak has sixty-three years to live, okay, because he
dies at a hundred and thirty-seven, okay, so ישמעאל Yishmael has sixty-three
years to live. Okay, so כמה פיישן משנוהי שישים ושלוש. kama paishen
mishnei shishim veshalosh. ותניא היה יעקב אבינו בשעה שנתברך מאביו בן שישים
ושלוש שנים. Vetanya haya Yaakov Avinu besha'ah shenitbarech me'aviv ben shishim veshalosh
shanim. So יעקב Yaakov was sixty-three when he was blessed by his
father, meaning when he was going to run away to
ארם נהריים. Aram Naharayim. ובו בפרק מת ישמעאל. Uvo baperek met Yishmael.
So when ישמעאל Yishmael died, יעקב Yaakov was sixty-three. So that's the
key of why we want to know how old ישמעאל Yishmael is,
because we're going to assume that at the date of ישמעאל's Yishmael's
death, when יעקב Yaakov was sixty-three, that's when he ran to ארם
נהריים. Aram Naharayim. Okay, now how what is going to allow us
to assume that that happened at the date of ישמעאל's Yishmael's death?
So let's take a look. דכתיב וירא עשיו כי ברך יצחק את
יעקב Dechtiv vayara Eisav ki berach Yitzchak et Yaakov etc. וישלח פדן
ארם vayishlach Padan Aram וילך עשיו אל ישמעאל ויקח את מחלת בת
ישמעאל אחות נביות לו לאשה. vayelech Eisav el Yishmael vayikach et Machalat
bat Yishmael achot Nevayot lo le'ishah. So עשיו Eisav went and he
married, because he saw his parents didn't like בנות כנען, benot Kena'an,
he married מחלת Machalat the daughter of ישמעאל Yishmael the sister of
נביות. Nevayot. ממשמע שנאמר בת ישמעאל איני יודע שהיא אחות נביות? Mimmashma
shene'emar bat Yishmael eini yode'a shehi achot Nevayot? Since she's the daughter
of ישמעאל, Yishmael, of course she's the sister of נביות Nevayot who
is ישמעאל's Yishmael's son. So why does it say the sister of
נביות? Nevayot? מלמד שקידשה ישמעאל ומת. Melamed shekiddshah Yishmael umet. So ישמעאל
Yishmael married her off, right, when she was underage or whatever, he
married her off to עשיו Eisav and then ישמעאל Yishmael died והשיאה
נביות אחיה vehisi'ah Nevayot achiha and therefore נביות Nevayot her brother had
to be the one to give her away at the at the
חופה, chuppah, okay, so at the actual נישואין. nisuin. So that we
know this is the key. We're going to assume that יעקב Yaakov
left at sixty-three because the way it speaks about עשיו Eisav marrying
and mentions the sister of נביות Nevayot means that ישמעאל Yishmael died
according to the גמרא, Gemara. and therefore that event happened when ישמעאל
Yishmael died, he was sixty-three. Okay, so that's point number one. Okay,
so שישים ושלוש shishim veshalosh now he was sixty-three, וארבע עשרה עד
דמתיליד יוסף, ve'arba esreh ad demitayallid Yosef, and he was fourteen more
years until יוסף was born, right, because it says right because if
you read the story that's what happens. יוסף is born he wants
to leave his fourteen years are up and then he agrees to
stay and he works six more years. So הרי שבעים ושבע. harei
shiv'im vesheva. So he was seventy-seven when יוסף was born. וכתיב יוסף
בן שלושים שנה בעמדו לפני פרעה. Uchtiv Yosef ben shloshim shanah be'omdo
lifnei Paroh. Now יוסף was thirty when he stood before פרעה, Paroh,
so that would make יעקב Yaakov a hundred and seven, המאה ושבע.
hamei'ah vasheva. Now after יוסף stands before פרעה, Paroh, how much longer
until יעקב Yaakov comes down? שבע דשבעא ותרתי דכפנא, Sheva deshav'a vetartei
dechafna, seven years of the of the plenty and two years of
the famine, המאה ושיבסר. hamei'ah veshivsar. So now that's nine more, so
now יעקב Yaakov should be a hundred and sixteen. So if you
do the math, יעקב Yaakov, is a hundred and sixteen. וכתיב ויאמר
פרעה אל יעקב כמה ימי שני חייך ויאמר יעקב אל פרעה ימי
שני מגורי שלושים ומאת שנה. Uchtiv vayomer Paroh el Yaakov kama yemei
shenei chayecha vayomer Yaakov el Paroh yemei shenei megurai shloshim ume'at shanah.
So he said he was a hundred and thirty. But wait a
minute, we did the math, he should have been a hundred and
sixteen. המאה ושיבסר הוו, Hamei'ah veshivsar havei, he should have been a
hundred and sixteen. אלא שמע מינה ארבע עשרה דהוה בבי עבר לא
חשיב להו. Ella shema mina arba esreh dehavah bevei Ever lo chashiv
lehu. It must be there were fourteen what happened to the mysterious
missing fourteen years? It must be those were fourteen years he spent
learning in the ישיבה yeshiva of עבר Ever and therefore he did
not those were what we were not counting and that's why we
got to a hundred and sixteen rather than a hundred and thirty.
דתניא היה יעקב בבית עבר מטמן, Detanya haya Yaakov beveit Ever mutman,
יעקב Yaakov was buried like was hidden, you know, went away to
learn, fourteen years, ארבע עשרה שנה. arba esreh shanah. Now עבר Ever
and part of the reason they associate it with עבר Ever is
because as the גמרא's Gemara about to say if you do also
the other math, עבר Ever dies right around the time that the
these fourteen years are up, so it sort of actually parallels what
we said before about עזרא Ezra made עליה aliyah right after his
רבי died, so here something similar, although actually it's two years off
here. הגמרא Hagemara says עבר מת אחר שירד יעקב אבינו לארם נהריים
שתי שנים. Ever met achar sherad Yaakov Avinu le'Aram Naharayim shtei shanim.
So you know maybe he was no longer giving שיעור, shiur, he
was it was his last two years, so that's when יעקב went
to ארם נהריים Aram Naharayim after fourteen years and if you do
the math you'll see that עבר Ever died two years later. יצא
משם ובא לו לארם נהריים נמצא כשאמד על הבאר בן שבעים ושבע
שנים. Yatza misham uva lo le'Aram Naharayim nimtza kesh'amad al habe'er ben
shiv'im vesheva shanim. He was seventy-seven when he stood by the באר
be'er if you add those fourteen years. Okay, so we've figured out
that there's a missing fourteen years. The explanation we give is that
he was in בית עבר, Beit Ever, which sort of works because
עבר Ever died towards the end a little bit after those fourteen
years. ומנלן דלא מיענש? Umenalan dila mi'anesh? How do you know he
wasn't punished for being absent from his from his parents? דתניא נמצא
יוסף שפירש מאביו עשרים ושתיים שנה. Detanya nimtza Yosef sheperash me'aviv esrim
ushtayim shanah. יוסף was seventeen when he was sold, and we just
did the math and he was thirty-nine when he was when he
was recon- when he was. brought back together with יעקב, that's twenty-two
years. כשם שפירש יעקב אבינו מאביו, Keshem shepeirash Yaakov Avinu me'aviv, and
that was the exact same twenty-two years that יעקב was not with
his parents or father. And now
what's the math? דיעקב תלתין ושיתא הוין. D'Yaakov tlatin ushita havin. We
just did the math that it was thirty-six. Now it's not exactly
clear how it's thirty-six because he has the fourteen for רחל Rachel
and לאה Leah and the six, right, for working for the sheep,
it's twenty, we've added fourteen, it's thirty-four, we'll see where we get
the other two years in a minute. But for now let's assume
thirty-six. So what do you mean he was only, he was away
from his father twenty-two years? He was away
thirty-six? אלא ארביסר דהוה בבי עבר לא חשיב להו. Ella arbisar d'havavei
bei Ever lo chashiv lehu. It must be that the fourteen that
he was in בית עבר, Beit Ever, those weren't counted. And that's
what we're coming out to prove that the תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
was greater than כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud Av V'Em. So the גמרא
Gemara says so סוף דבי לבן עשרין שנין הוין. Sof d'bei Lavan
esrin shanin havin. One minute. But still we only have twenty years.
We don't have twenty-two years. Even if you don't count the fourteen,
basically we added fourteen and now we created a problem that there
are fourteen extra. Because fourteen extra in terms of this idea that
he suffered twenty-two for the twenty-two he was away from his father.
So we take the fourteen away that we added in order to
solve the problem and it shows that he wasn't punished for those
fourteen years. But now we've got a problem, we only know it
was really only twenty years. אלא משום דאשתהי באורחא תרתין שנין. Ella
mishum d'ishtahei be'orcha tartin shanin. It was two more years getting back.
דתניא, Detanya, we taught a ברייתא, braitah, יצא מארם נהרים ובא לסוכות
ועשה שם שמונה עשר חודש. Yatza me'Aram Naharayim uva l'Succoth v'asah sham
shmonah asar chodesh. He went from ארם נהרים Aram Naharayim and he
came to סוכות Succoth on his way back and he spent eighteen
months. שנאמר ויעקב נסע סכתה ויבן לו בית ולמקנהו עשה סכת. Shene'emar
v'Yaakov nasa Succothah vayiven lo bayit ulemiknehu asah Succoth. סוכות Succoth is
what you build in the summer and then there's a house which
is for presumably the interim period or whatever and then he did
סוכות Succoth again which is the next summer. So summer and then
winter
and then summer is eighteen months. ובבית אל עשה ששה חדשים והקריב
זבחים. Uv'Beit El asah shishah chodashim v'hikriv zvachim. And somehow we'll add
six more months for בית אל, Beit El, we get the two
years. So basically we're able to say that it was twenty-two years
away and that's equivalent to the twenty-two that he wasn't around his
parents, but then there's fourteen missing, from the fourteen we added is
missing, so it shows you he wasn't punished for those fourteen years.
Now by the way this is interesting because number one, you raise
questions which I'm not going to go into about כיבוד אב ואם
Kibbud Av V'Em which is, you know, his mother told him to
go away and his father as he blessed him to go away.
Now you could say it means okay, he didn't have to take
that long, he shouldn't have, didn't have to work for fourteen years,
maybe he should have figured out another arrangement, he didn't have to
work for six years afterwards, he certainly didn't have to wait two
years coming back. But it's not that the whole twenty-two years were
time that he should have been at home. They told him to
go. So part of the question again here is is this saying
a הלכה halakhic statement or is this sort of saying look, it
might be that you have a good justifiable reason for not being
with your parents, but at the same time it doesn't mean that
you're not having the opportunity to do כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud Av
V'Em. It doesn't mean you're necessarily doing something you shouldn't be doing,
doing something wrong, but there's a reality of not having that opportunity.
And look, there's very important הלכה halakhic questions about כיבוד אב ואם
Kibbud Av V'Em about what it means if somebody has to take
a job out of state halfway around the world, and it might
be that the הלכה halakhah is okay, that comes before כיבוד אב
ואם, Kibbud Av V'Em, but there's still a real-world impact of what
it means not to be able to be close to one's parents
and to do the מצוה mitzvah in the same way. So that's
I just think one important thing and again it raises this question
about the sort of real-world aspect of something or the value of
something as opposed to sort of the הלכה halakhic mandate of it.
And again I'll point out by the way that this issue about,
okay, תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is greater than כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud
Av V'Em. So to one degree you sort of have that expressed
in הלכה halakhah which is, you want to learn at a certain
ישיבה Yeshiva and your parents tell you oh no, we don't want
you to go there or we want you to stay at home,
and the הלכה halakhah is that you actually go learn where you
think you'll learn best. Now part of that has to do because
technically כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av V'Em is not just, is not
really about listening to one's parents, don't tell the kids this. It's
about attending to their needs and showing them honor and so on.
So the actual need to just listen and obey might not technically
be, but even if going to learn in a ישיבה Yeshiva takes
you away from your opportunity to do כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av
V'Em like we've been talking about, that actually is the הלכה. halakhah.
On the other hand, if here I am and I'm learning a
דף גמרא daf Gemara and my father says bring me a glass
of water or something, I stop learning and I bring him a
glass of water. That's the מצוה mitzvah of כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud
Av V'Em. It does take precedence over the act of תלמוד תורה.
Talmud Torah. So again these things are in an interesting dialectic with
one another and again to repeat the point I made before that
the exact same things here we say תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is
more important and בניין בית המקדש, Binyan Beit Hamikdash, מרדכי's Mordechai role
in הצלת נפשות hatzalat nefashot and so on, in הלכה halakhah actually
the reverse is true. So these things sort of remain in an
ongoing tension. Yes. I'm thinking not only having to take a job
out of town but voluntarily making עלייה aliyah when your parents stay
here. Right, right, but that's maybe even easier because it's about עלייה
aliyah whatever, but yes, all of those are very. the aspects of
the walled cities, the unwalled cities and very sort of central themes
about the nature of the, as I said, about
the מצוה mitzvah of מגילה, you know, sort of the way that
was it sort of became
a new מצוה, mitzvah, the ספר of the מגילה and so on.
Now this פרק perek turns us more to the technical aspects, technical
halachic aspects of the מצוה mitzvah of reading the מגילה. Let's take
a look. הקורא את המגילה למפרע לא יצא. Hakorei es haMegilla lemafrea
lo yatza. If you read it backwards, you're not יצא. yotzei. I
don't assume it means each word is backwards, but okay, you read
like a later פרק perek before an earlier פרק. perek. קרא על
פה, Kara al peh, if you read it orally without reading it
from the scroll, קרא תרגום, Kara Targum, or you read it in
translation, בכל לשון, Bechol lashon, or in any language, meaning you might
think that the Aramaic translation is better, לא יצא, Lo yatza, you
do not fulfill your obligation. אבל קורין אותה ללעוזות בלעז, Aval korin
osa liloazos bilaaz, you can read it to a foreigner in their
foreign language. So the גמרא's Gemara going to ask, what's that difference
between saying you can't read it in translation? והלועז ששמע אשורית יצא.
Vehaloez sheshama Ashuris yatza. Similarly, however, a foreigner who hears the Hebrew
script, now it's funny, אשורית Ashuris really refers to the script, but
presumably here it means Hebrew, right? Because it's also being read from
the scroll, so you could of course write one character type of
character script to write another language, but anyway, the, but if you
hear it in Hebrew, you're יצא yotzei even if you don't understand
it. קראה סירוגין ומתנמנם, Karaah seirugin umisnamnem, if you read it with
breaks or when you were dozing off, יצא, Yatza, you've fulfilled your
obligation. היה כותבה דורשה ומגיהה. Haya koshva dorsha umagiha. Let's say you
were writing the מגילה and as you were writing it, you were
like, you know, writing דרשות drosos about it or you were saying
over דרשות drosos or you weren't even realizing that you were saying
out the words, right? You were writing it down and then you
were sort of saying it in your giving of a דרשה, drasha
but not sort of consciously in terms of doing the מצוה, mitzvah,
or you were correcting the מגילה scroll and you were, you know,
you were verbalizing as you were reading but as you were correcting
but you weren't consciously doing it for the sake of the מצוה.
mitzvah. Wait, does it mean also the מגילה too when you're giving
your דרשה or just saying it over? Let's even say no, even
without saying other things, that's not the point here. So אם כיוון
ליבו יצא, Im kiven libo yatza, if you have intent to do
the מצוה mitzvah or at least this is the classic question of
the סוגיות sugyos of כוונה, kavana, at least the intent to do
an act of reading, maybe not to do, maybe you weren't even
aware that you were verbalizing the words, so minimally
you have to be aware that you're
reading and you might have to be aware that you're doing a
מצוה, mitzvah, then you're יצא. yotzei. ואם לאו לא יצא, Veim lav
lo yatza, if not, you are not, you do not fulfill your
obligation. היתה כתובה בסם ובסיקרא ובקומוס ובקנקנתום, Haysa kesuva besam uvesikra uvekumus
uvekankantum, if it was written in all these various types of inks,
על הנייר, Al hanyar, if it's written on a paper which means...
how did they make paper in the ancient world? Cloth, right? It
was some type of a... anyway, ועל הדפתרא, Veal hadiphtera, which is
a type of a leather-based parchment but not קלף, klaf, לא יצא,
Lo yatza, you do not fulfill, עד שתהא כתובה אשורית על הספר
ובדיו. Ad shetehei kesuva Ashuris al hasefer uvidyo. So it has to
be written in Hebrew, which gets back to the earlier point about
other languages. It has to be written on ספר, which means on
קלף, klaf, and with דיו, dyo, which is the ink that הלכה
Halacha recognizes. So we'll discuss all of those particular things about the
type of קלף klaf and the type of ink later. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara מנא הני מילי? Manani milei? Where
do you get this from? That it has... you can't read it
backwards. אמר רבה דאמר קרא, Amar Rabba deamar kra, because the verse
says ככתבם וכזמנם, Keichsavim uchezmanim, like their writing and in their times.
מה זמנם למפרע לא, Mah zmanim lemafrea lo, the same way time
doesn't go backwards, so or you don't do, observe, you know, the
15th celebration before the 14th, אף כתבם למפרע לא, Af ksavam lemafrea
lo, even what's written about them, you do not do it backwards.
So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, מידי קריאה כתיב הכא?
עשייה כתיב הכא. Midi keria kesiv hacha? Asiya kesiv hacha. It says
להיות עושים liyos osim to do these days ככתבם וכזמנם. keichsavim uchezmanim.
It doesn't say to read, it's not talking about the act of
reading, it's talking about the act of observance. דכתיב להיות עושים את
שני הימים, Dechsiv liyos osim es shenei hayamim, אלא מהכא, Ela mehacha,
from here, דכתיב והימים האלה נזכרים ונעשים, Dechsiv vehayamim ha'eileh nizkarim venaasim,
these days are remembered and performed. So remembered is about reading. איתקש
זכירה לעשייה, Iskash zchira laasiya, connects memory to doing. מה עשייה למפרע
לא, Mah asiya lemafrea lo, the same way you don't observe it
backwards, you don't do the walled cities before the unwalled, אף זכירה
למפרע לא, Af zchira lemafrea lo, you don't do the mentioning of
it, the remembering of it backwards, you do it in the right
order. So the גמרא Gemara says תנא וכן בהלל וכן בקריאת שמע
ובתפילה. Tana vechein beHallel vechein beKrias Shema uvitfilla. Similarly by הלל, Hallel,
קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, and תפילה. Tefilla. So מנא לן? Manalan? How
do you know this? That they have to be in this particular
order, in the, in their order. רבה אמר דאמר קרא דכתיב, Rabba
amar deamar kra dechsiv, because the verse says ממזרח שמש עד מבואו,
mimizrach shemesh ad mevo'o, from the rising of the sun to its
setting. So the same way that's in a particular order and that's
about, you know, these פסוקים psukim in הלל, Hallel, so that speaks
about saying them in order. רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar זה
היום עשה ה׳, Zeh hayom asa Hashem, so like a day occurs,
you know, in order. רב אוויא אמר Rav Avya amar יהי שם
ה׳ מבורך, Yehi shem Hashem mevorach, which isn't as clear but רש״י
Rashi says יהי yehi means as it normally occurs in its natural
order. רב נחמן בר יצחק ואיתימא רב אחא בר יעקב. Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak veisima Rav Acha bar Yaakov. רב אחא בר יעקב Rav
Acha bar Yaakov מהכא mehacha מעתה ועד עולם, me'ata ve'ad olam, from
now forever, again that's a certain sequence. Now, of course, saying הלל
Hallel is not a biblical מצוה. mitzvah. רמב"ן Ramban thinks that there
is a biblical מצוה, mitzvah, right, to say הלל Hallel on ימים
טובים, Yamim Tovim, but not obviously these particular פרקים perakim in תהלים.
Tehillim. Nevertheless, what the rabbis are doing is they chose those פרקים
perakim and they might, you know, some traditions maybe using דוקא davka
those פרקים, perakim, it goes way way back to the time that
דוד המלך Dovid Hamelech wrote it, or an idea that it goes
way back. So therefore they understand that there is a very particular
order here that has to be followed and seen it from within
the פסוקים psukim themselves. קריאת שמע דתניא, Krias Shema de'tanya, קריאת שמע
Krias Shema because it says so, קריאת שמע ככתבה, Krias Shema ke'chsava,
we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, it has to be you have
to say it the way it's written. You can't do it in
translation. דברי רבי. Divrei Rebbi. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim בכל לשון, bechol
lashon, you can do it in translation, which is how we פסקן,
pasken, which is important, like people that are not, you know, don't
know Hebrew or whatever and they're becoming more observant and you can
say it in translation. מאי טעמא דרבי? Mai ta'ama de'Rebbi? What's the
reason of רבי? אמר קרא amar kra because the verse says והיו
והיו, ve'hayu ve'hayu, so that they should be והיו הדברים האלה. ve'hayu
ha'devarim ha'eleh. So they have to be exactly exactly as they are
written in their natural state in Hebrew. דרבנן מאי טעמא, Derabbanan mai
ta'ama, why do the rabbis say it can be in translation? אמר
קרא amar kra the verse says שמע, Shema, שמע ישראל Shema Yisrael
בכל לשון שאתה שומע, bechol lashon she'ata shome'a, however you're able to
understand it. It's more about understanding and saying its meaning than about
saying the particular text in which it was written, the exact text
as it was written. So ולרבי נמי הא כתיב שמע, ve'Rebbi nami
ha ksiv Shema, it says שמע, Shema, why does it have to
say שמע? Shema? Why doesn't it just say ישראל? Anyway, ההוא מיבעי
ליה השמע לאזנך מה שאתה מוציא מפיך. Hahu miba'lei hashmia le'oznecha ma
she'ata motzi mipicha. He uses that to say that you have to
be able to hear the words you're saying. It's not enough just
to mouth them. ורבנן סברי כמאן דאמר הקורא שמע ולא השמיע לאזנו
יצא, Verabbanan savri keman de'amar hakorei Shema velo hishmia le'ozno yatza, and
the rabbis say even if you aren't able to hear them, you're
יצא. yatza. I should point out that there is a link of
these two positions, right. רבי focuses more on the ritual nature of
the act, you know, doing or like the sort of external type,
so it has to be a very particular text, it has to
be verbalized, right. It's getting to the, you know, the way in
which it objectively is said and performed, whereas the rabbis are a
little bit more focused on the, you know, the meaning, not the
meaning of the מצוה, mitzvah, but like the meaning of the words,
less on sort of just the ritual of saying. So they allow
it even if you're not saying it out loud, even if you're
just verbalizing, even if you're saying it in translation. You know, it's
sort of it's still is something that you're saying to yourself and
that has meaning to yourself, right? I mean, and therefore, so there
to me there seems to be this that there's a link between
these two positions. That רבי wants more, you know, sort of more
criteria in terms of the formal ritual act than than the rabbis
do. And the rabbis are willing to sort of say, look, you
know, you're understanding what you're saying, you don't have to make it
into a ritual act of a particular text and being said like
דוקא davka of being able to hear what you're saying. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara now just says like this. ורבנן סברי, Verabbanan savri,
oh we just did that. ורבנן נמי הא כתיב והיו, Verabbanan nami
ha ksiv ve'hayu, which makes it mean like in their original state.
ההוא מיבעי ליה שלא יקרא למפריע, Hahu miba'lei shelo yikra lemafre'ia, which
is what why we're quoting this, so you can't read it backwards.
ולרבי שלא יקרא למפריע מנא ליה? Ve'Rebbi shelo yikra lemafre'ia minalei? How
does he know you can't do it backwards? And you might think
that that's implicit, I mean if you can't do it in translation.
So מהדברים הדברים והיו הדברים, me'hadevarim ha'devarim ve'hayu ha'devarim, the words means
exactly the way they're presented. ורבנן הדברים הדברים לא משמע להו, Verabbanan
hadvarim hadvarim lo mashma lehu, and the rabbis don't feel you have
to make a דרשה out of that. Okay, now the גמרא has
one other point about this. לימא קסבר רבי כל התורה כולה בכל
לשון נאמרה. Leima kasavar Rebbi kol haTorah kullah bechol lashon ne'emrah. Let's
say רבי holds the whole תורה Torah was said in in in
all languages. Now what does it mean the תורה Torah was said
in all languages? So רש"י Rashi says it means that you could
be you could read the תורה Torah. in all languages. Of course
תוספות Tosafot says, first of all, that's debated. Second of all, well,
but that's what's saying. But okay, but second of all, there's no
מצוה mitzvah in the תורה Torah to read the תורה. Torah So
what really it seems to me is when the תורה tells you
you have to say things like מקרא ביכורים, mikra bikkurim, right, ארמי
אובד אבי. Arami oved avi. There's other there are places in the
תורה where it speaks about saying certain things, like they stand on
הר גריזים והר עיבל Har Gerizim ve'Har Eival and they say ארור
האיש Arur ha'ish etc. There are various recitations in the תורה. Is
the תורה should what's the default? Are we default supposed to assume
that those can be said in translation, or we default supposed to
assume that they can only be said in Hebrew? So that's the
גמרא says, let's say that's what's this debate. לימא קסבר רבי כל
התורה כולה בכל לשון נאמרה. Leima kasavar Rebbi kol haTorah kullah bechol
lashon ne'emrah. Maybe רבי holds generally that the תורה could be said
in any language, any of the recitations. דאי סלקא דעתך בלשון הקודש
נאמרה, De'i salka da'atach bilshon hakodesh ne'emrah, if the default is it
has to be Hebrew, למה לי למכתב והיו? lama li limchtav ve'hayu?
Why would it have to say והיו? ve'hayu? So it's obviously a
little counter-intuitive, but the גמרא is saying if you need והיו ve'hayu
to tell you שמע Shema is in Hebrew, the implication is that
the rule is that the default rule is any language. But גמרא
says no, איצטריך, istrich, you need it סלקא דעתך שמע כרבנן. salka
da'atach Shema kerabbanan. because the word שמע *Shema* might have suggested that
it could be any language, so כתב רחמנא והיו *kasav rachmana vehayu*.
So no, maybe the default is Hebrew, but you still needed והיו
*vehayu* to insist on Hebrew so you shouldn't come to make a
mistake by שמע *Shema*. So now the גמרא *Gemara* is going to
do the same thing for the רבנן *Rabbanan*. לימא קסברי רבנן כל
התורה בלשון הקודש נאמרה *Leima kasvari rabanan kol hatorah belashon hakodesh neemra*?
Let's say the רבנן *Rabbanan* who say שמע *Shema* is in any
language, say the default is that everything has to be in לשון
הקודש *lashon hakodesh*. דאי סלקא דעתך כל התורה נאמרה *De'i salka deitach
kol hatorah neemra*, if the default is any language, למה לי למכתב
שמע *lama li lemichtav Shema*? Then you wouldn't need the word שמע
*Shema* to tell you any language, the default is any language. No,
איצטריך *itztriech*. You would still need the word שמע *Shema*. סלקא דעתך
אמינא והיו כרבי *Salka deitach amina vehayu ke-Rabbi*. והיו *Vehayu* would have
pulled me רבי *Rabbi*'s way to say Hebrew, כתב רחמנא שמע *kasav
rachmana Shema*,
so it says שמע *Shema*. The upshot of all this is that
it's not necessarily what you
say by שמע *Shema* is not necessarily what you say by other
recitations. But it raises a general question when there are recitations in
the תורה *Torah*, are they to be understood to be specifically in
Hebrew or are they supposed to be in any language? And there's
a debate by שמע *Shema*, it could be the same debate, it
could be a different debate. Again, I think it's interesting the way
רבי *Rabbi* who demands the Hebrew, Hebrew also demands a particular way
of articulating and of saying it in a way that can be
heard. Now did I skip a line about no I didn't. Okay
maybe it's coming up later. Alright there is something that gets to
the idea about נזכרים ונעשים *nizkarim ve-naasim*. Why זכירה *zachira* means to
verbalize and not just to think in your head, right? Why does
it mean to actually do an act of reading? I think that's
going to come up more tomorrow, but it's a point about that
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* makes in his book זכור *Zachor*, which is the whole
ways in which Jews our memory is a form of ritualizing, of
remembering and not just thinking about something, but actually memorializing something through
ritual act and creating the memory through ritual act. That's clearly the
גמרא *Gemara* about נזכרים *nizkarim* is about the act of reading the
מגילה *Megillah*, something that we will return to. Let's at least start
now the final point here. So we did שמע *Shema*, we did
מגילה *Megillah*, let's now talk about שמונה עשרה *Shmoneh Esrei*. Okay תפילה
מנלן *tfillah minalan*? How do you know תפילה *tfillah* has to be
in order? דתניא *Detanya*, it's in a ברייתא *baraita*: שמעון הפקולי הסדיר
שמונה עשרה ברכות לפני רבן גמליאל על הסדר ביבנה *Shimon Hapakuli hesdir
shmoneh esrei berachot lifnei Rabban Gamliel al haseder be-Yavneh*. שמעון הפקולי *Shimon
Hapakuli*, practically I think he was a cotton trader or seller, organized
the, arranged the 18 ברכות *berachot* before רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* of
the order in יבנה *Yavneh*. So he didn't author them, there were
these ברכות *berachot* that were out there and people were saying them,
there were different variations of it, but he constructed it in this
particular order in this particular text in front of רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel*. אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא *Amar Rabbi Yochanan ve-amrei
lah bematnita tana*: מאה ועשרים זקנים ובהם כמה נביאים תיקנו שמונה עשרה
ברכות על הסדר *me'ah ve-esrim zekenim uvahem kama nevi'im tiknu shmoneh esrei
berachot al haseder*. Was it שמעון הפקולי *Shimon Hapakuli*? The גמרא *Gemara*
is going to try to reconcile these two traditions. But anyway, it
was 120 elders and some of them were prophets going back to
the prophet and elder scene that we had before. They arranged the
18 ברכות *berachot* in this order. And now the גמרא *Gemara* is
going to go through the 18 ברכות *berachot*. Let's at least get
started. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*: מנין שאומרים אבות *minayin she'omrim avot*? שנאמר
*shenemar*: הבו לה' בני אלים *havu la-Hashem bnei eilim*. Give to God
like the rams, meaning the strong ones, the forebears, אברהם יצחק ויעקב
*Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov*. ומנין שאומרים גבורות *Uminayin she'omrim gevurot*? שנאמר *shenemar*: הבו
לה' כבוד ועוז *havu la-Hashem kavod va-oz*, honor and strength. ומנין שאומרים
קדושות *Uminayin she'omrim kedushot*? שנאמר *shenemar*: הבו לה' כבוד שמו השתחוו לה'
בהדרת קודש *havu la-Hashem kvod shemo hishtachavu la-Hashem behadrat kodesh*. So that
opening up with praise to God before you get to the more
בקשה *bakasha* part seen as reflected in these פסוקים *psukim* are seen
to be praise in specifically this type of order. Of course, it
doesn't really help us too much in trying to understand the theme
and the structure. I'll just say one word about that, opening up
with the אבות *avot*, and I think רב סולובייצ'יק *Rav Soloveitchik* talks
about this a good deal, what bothers סולובייצ'יק *Soloveitchik* a lot by
דאווענינג *davenning* is how does a human being, what gives a human
being a right or how can you even think about the idea
of what it means for a finite corporeal human being to approach
God in prayer? So to some degree he talks about סמיכת גאולה
לתפילה *smichat ge'ulah litfillah* as allowing that and that's another discussion. But
also the אבות *avot* is basically you're saying we're not doing it,
we're historic, we're doing what our forefathers did and they've already paved
the way, they've somehow legitimated us to come and approach and to
do this. And then of course you recognize God's power and you
recognize God's קדוש *kadosh*, which is God as not just transcendent but
the enormous gap that exists between you and God. So all those
three together acknowledge the challenge of what it means to be standing
in prayer. God is all powerful and God is so completely different
than us, which is גבורות *gevurot* and קדושות *kedushot*, and then also
but the אבות *avot* is what allows that beginning and that entry
to the שמונה עשרה *Shmoneh Esrei*. So we will continue with this
tomorrow.